what's up everybody this is Nick at
bobbin.com and today we're going to walk
you through how we landed on the best
branch chain amino acid supplements on
the market
BCAAs they are an unbelievably popular
supplement on the market after like whey
protein and creatine BCAAs they seem to
be the most widespread supplement if you
go to a Sports Nutrition store and the
reason for that is if they're widely
considered a means to potentially help
to improve muscle retention like avoid
muscle loss during difficult workouts
and maybe to have other potential
ergogenic benefits as well maybe they'll
help you have longer workouts maybe that
helps to increase Focus we're going to
go through a bit of the research later
on in today's less we're gonna be going
through the best overall the best and
best so women best of fat loss and more
so make absolutely sudden you stick
around little disclaimer uh I'm not a
doctor this is not medical advice that's
something we've got to get out there if
you're making any big changes to your
diet or your exercise regimen or your
supplement regimen make sure you speak
to a qualified medical professional do
make sure your uncle have any
interactions with medications or
pre-existing conditions it's all just to
make sure that it's right for you so
make sure you do that before we go any
further as well uh why don't I just tell
you what the best BCAA is I know that's
what you're here for that's why you're
clicking this video so I respect your
time I'm going to tell you it's
Wolverine it's really nice and simple
it's just like what you want from a BCAA
company uh a lot of the time these sorts
of products have a whole lot of extra
weird ingredients they may need to have
benefits but they ratchet up the price
they may not be exactly what you're
looking for this has a solid ratio of
leucine isoleucine and battling the
three BCAAs plus one or two other
ingredients that may further enhance
muscle retention and improve energy
throughout your workout I'm going to
talk about that in a little bit and also
going to get two packs for the best pcas
for endurance athletes the best
pre-workout with BCAAs and a whole lot
more but for now why take them amino
acids are often called the building
blocks of protein protein is made up of
many amino acids essential amino acids
are one ones that we cannot make
ourselves so you have to get it through
food and the three branched chain amino
acids so named for their little branched
looks if you consume under microscope
leucine isoleucine and Valium leucine is
most closely associated with muscle
protein synthesis but that effect seems
to be a little bit boosted or enhanced
by the inclusion of isoleucine and
valine which may have extra potential
benefits such as focus and endurance so
that's what BCAAs are why do you take
them there's some research that suggests
that when you're exercising a few things
happen in the body like you have a serum
like a decline in the BCAAs in your
blood which can help which can lead to
like reductions in performance when
you're exercising right so there's some
research that suggests that taking
supplemental BCAAs can help to prevent
or reduce that decline in BCAAs in your
blood and thereby help to improve your
like sort of endurance and how long you
can have an effective workout for it's
also possible that it helps to lower the
loss of muscle glycogen when you're
exercising and thereby again help you to
work out for a little bit longer so by
also mitigating that reduction in serum
BCAAs the idea is that they can help to
reduce fatigue
also listing is closely related as I
mentioned to muscle protein synthesis so
a lot of folks
if they are not getting enough protein
in their diet like if you aren't
reaching the generally recommended by
Sports nutritionist level of
0.721 gram of protein per pound of body
weight per day if you're not reaching
that a lot of folks take supplemental
branched chain amino acids so that they
can stimulate muscle protein synthesis
in the absence of real food right so
basically if you're getting a ton of
protein throughout the day already it's
unlikely that you're going to need to
take BCAAs like between meals that said
plenty of folks who either didn't get
around to getting enough protein in the
day or if they're having a really long
gap between meals or if they're fasting
a lot of folks like to take BCAAs as
well in that regard plus it just tastes
really good as well right Tom Stoltman
who wound up winning the World's
Strongest Man twice after I interviewed
him on this he said he just takes BCAAs
throughout the day just to make sure
that he drinks enough water and also
again if you're having a long break
between meals they can help to stimulate
muscle protein synthesis
that's BCAAs
[Music]
top pick small Marines two to one to one
BCAA formula we like this so much we
named it as the best overall also the
best for weight loss and also the best
for electrolytes it's got a whole lot
going for it so research has suggested
that with the three branch amino acids
leucine isolucin and Valium you want two
parts leucine to one part eye solution
and Valium that is the best research
supported ratio that's what scorpion has
used here but the ingredients list is
actually quite minimalist which is what
another thing that we liked about it it
has those three BCAAs right it has some
extra additions may be useful like so
for weight loss for example people who
are looking to lose weight you want to
lose as much fat as you can retain as
much as you can I've already gone over
the evidence suggesting that BCAAs on
their own can help one to retain muscle
during exercise or during long breaks
between protein that kind of thing but
what else Wolverine does here is they
add in glutamine and vitamin B6 which
may have an extra effect there there's
some evidence that glutamine is good for
gut health but there's also some
evidence that it may help to reduce
post-exercise muscle soreness that's
more of a comfort thing but still that's
pretty nice now vitamin B6 may seem like
an unusual addition in a product like
this like it's just some way to say it
has more nutrition than your average
pcaa but vitamin B6 actually plays an
interesting role in fuel metabolism
during exercise like vitamin B6 helps
with protein building and muscle
retention during exercise and since we
appear in some research we appear to
lose vitamin B6 as we exercise it's
actually not a bad idea to have vitamin
B6 in what is typically taken as a
pre-workout sub supplement like the
Wolverines there are also some
electrolation here some sodium and
potassium
electrolyte supplementation especially
sodium honestly I think personally that
it's a really undisturbed and
underemphasized area in Sports Nutrition
we lose electrolytes when we sweat
that's why your sweat is salty and it
really is a very very good idea to
ensure you're getting electrolytes
especially sodium throughout the day and
especially before you work out this
contains both sodium and potassium in it
there are other electrons out there like
calcium and that kind of stuff for some
folks sodium and potassium they're a
little bit less likely to go from Whole
Foods so that's why
you want to get a product like this has
a bit of exercise testing in it it's got
a bit of extra glutamine for reducing
muscle soreness and for a healthy gut
you got some B6 to enhance the muscle
retention properties any of the BCAAs
themselves to help with muscle retention
only with other BCAAs do so the downside
is lemon lime is the only flavor they
have and I think that's because they
went the route of having no artificial
flavoring because BCAAs on their own
naturally they're actually quite bitter
and you typically need like quite a lot
of like nice strong flavoring to
overpower the flavor of BCAAs and when
you're using natural flavorings uh
people you have to typically add some
sourness to make them have some flavors
the flavor is your number one priority
plenty of other products here for you
let's move on to the next pick next
thing we're going to talk about the best
BCAAs for muscle growth so this is a
little bit different of a category to
weight loss which is typically by
calorie deficits muscle growth is
typically about calorie excess extra
calories so those are two very different
goals we're talking about the BCAA is
something from huge supplements which we
think is the best for muscle growth we
don't is the best for men and also we
think this is the best BCA supplement
for workouts like for taking during your
workouts to enhance your workout
performance right so again uh when you
are trying to gain muscle you're not in
the calorie deficit your energy levels
are typically pretty good so something
like this uh you take it to enhance your
workouts as opposed to
preventing a massive uh increase in
fatigue during your workouts if that
makes sense so what we've got here is a
supplement that for one has a really
good dose of 8 grams of branched amino
acids that's a very high dose of them so
that's very good in addition to that
they've got other amino acids in here as
well so this gets into the kind of murky
territorial comparing Branch to amino
acid supplements with essential amino
acid supplements but long story short
BCAAs are the universe's most closely
associated with muscle protein synthesis
and muscle retention but throwing in
some extra amino acids can potentially
have a more useful effect right so BCAAs
are sort of like the minimum effective
dose of amino acids to potentially
impact on Supreme synthesis but a lot of
people like to add in extra amino acids
like an essential amino acid supplement
to help to further enhance that muscle
protein synthesis response so in
addition to the three Ranch amino acids
there's also an extra six essential
amino acids in this product that hugeot
supplements has added in there so that
could potentially make it a better pick
if muscle growth is your number one
priority the other reason that we named
this the best branched chain amino acid
supplement for workouts is because well
this nice high dosage should have a good
anti-fatigue effect but on top of that
we need this one the best for men
because frankly it just has a higher
dose so men tend to weigh more than
women this is sort of how it works and
so the bigger the athlete the stronger
the dose of things they tend to need
right so female athletes will often
recommend to take pre-workouts that are
lower in caffeine than some of the
others because they tend to have lower
body weight so therefore you know high
caffeine counts can affect them a little
bit more because this has such a high
dose and eight grams of ranch amino
acids this is very effective for both
people of lower body weights and people
of larger body weights hence this being
a good pick for men as well plus not to
mention the fact that it helps with a
post-workout muscle soreness which is
quite widely reported among males doing
a lot of those really heavy hypertrophy
High rep muscle building workouts so me
and the other guys at Bob and big fans
of the huge supplements bcae now before
I go any further I know I'm kind of
throwing a lot of information at you
here if you would rather read it
yourself at your own pace without my
accent you can you can just Google bar
band best BCAA and that'll take you
right to the article version of this
video with all these studies we've been
talking about and that'll help you make
the decision that's right for you oh we
can keep talking so let's move on to on
its total strength performance plan
which we don't have because we use it
all because it was very popular among
the barbed office what was interesting
about on its BCAA is that it was a BCA
supplement that also functioned as a
non-stem pre-workout so those of us who
take pre-workouts without caffeine in
them would often take this one because
it has ingredients that were
anti-inflammatory and anti-estrogenic
stuff like luteolin and long Jack and
that kind of stuff and vitamin B6 and a
lot of these very old natural
ingredients like plenty of plant
extracts that may have anti-inflammatory
benefits that kind of thing plus there's
no artificial flavors or Sweetness in it
right now we couldn't get another tub
because on is reformulating it but
overall we've been really impressed with
their products in the past and the way
that they mixed in BCAAs with like
really natural plant extracts that might
have extra like ergogenic and Recovery
benefits we found it really impressive
so we're really hanging out to see it
when it comes back to Market so if
you're looking for the best BCAA blend
Ana does a really good job of like
combining a lot of different ingredients
in there that have interesting effects
while still remaining like fairly
holistic grounded in whole Foodie in the
supplement game so they're very unique
they really send out in the marketplace
a curious question we often receive is
what is the best protein how to with
BCAAs it's an interesting one because
amino acids are the building blocks of
protein BCAAs are actually already very
high in Whey Protein itself like whey is
actually considered the most
bioavailable protein in the world which
means it's the most readily absorbed
largely because of how fantastic that
amino acid profile is so our favorite
there's got to be this one right here
it's swold Marines so Wolverines whey
protein powder it's very legit it is uh
all whey protein isolate so there's no
concentrate in there which means it
doesn't have like the lactose or sugars
it doesn't agree with some people this
is not like 100 sugar-free uh there's
one gram per scoop but like if you were
talking about whey concentrate that's
going to have yeah more lactose and more
fat this is that really really paired
down so the protein per calorie is very
very high because of that persistent way
approaching isolate and on top of that
it's got digestive enzymes too which is
really cool I'm a big fan of when
they're at enzymes in these sorts of
supplements the proteases there are a
wide range of enzymes and all there's
light paces down fat and so on but
proteases some research has suggested
that taking that with your protein can
help to enhance the way it is absorbed
and enhance how quickly it's absorbed as
well so Sovereign bunch of really tasty
flavors no artificial flavors and uh
yeah we're constantly chugging it around
here at bobbin all right so next up
what's the best pre-workout with BCAAs
the wedding that might be a bit funny
because for a lot of folks they've got
to take BCAAs before a workout that is
their pre-workout but this question is
like what's a pre-workout supplement
like with a bunch of other ingredients
that are meant to enhance performance
that also happens to contain BCAAs right
so BCAAs actually fairly uncommon in
pre-workouts pre-workouts are typically
caffeine and usually some combination of
like citrulline beta-alanine maybe beta
in creatine that kind of stuff we've got
plenty of content on pre-workouts I
encourage you to check out and in them
we heavily emphasize cage pre-cage this
is a really really solid pre-workout and
it has branched amino acids in it so in
addition to three and a half grams of
beef caas this has just more ingredients
and you can shake a sticker right it's
got like six and a half grams of
citrulline which has really strong links
with like blood flow uh like increased
blood flow extra endurance extra power
they've done interesting studies on
cyclists and tennis players showing
enhanced performance with that in
addition they've got interesting
ingredients linked to increased power
output like beta in anhydrous which is
found in beets the direct studies on a
bench press and squat with a increase
when you're taking beta in and there's
even a whole bunch of ground up fruits
and vegetables it's called a spectro
total orac blend it's kind of like a
little bit of a green superfood powder
like those greens powders with like
Blended up spirulina and stuff in them
so this in addition to BCAAs and all
these pre-workout ingredients and a
whopping 274 milligrams of caffeine
there's also ground up like broccoli
sprouts and blackcurrant juice and that
kind of stuff just as an extra
antioxidants and make it a little bit
more anti-inflammatory boy is it a good
pre-workout if you're looking fine with
BCAAs look no further next up we're
going to take a look at transparent Labs
which is one of our favorite supplement
companies because they're very
transparent as some somebody works in
the supplement industry I can tell you
there are a whole lot of supplements out
there that just don't tell you what's in
them or how much of everything that's in
them they hide things behind proprietary
blends to tell you what's in them but
not how much the idea is that so that
they don't have to tell you their secret
formula so that you can't copy it but
the real reason is so that they don't
tell you how much is in their product of
these ingredients because they probably
aren't an effective dose right anyway
transparent Labs is like a whole company
founded in response to that they don't
like this opaqueness in the industry so
they'll give you the exact amount of
everything they're putting in there and
also on the website they'll tell you
exactly why they made this product as
well and why they include those
ingredients transparent Labs branching
amino acids and glutamine this product
has glutamine and we consider it the
best tasting Branch tanning you nice to
product on the market in addition to
that is the best vegan BCAA as well the
flavors really really good transparent
Labs which is very shocking because they
also don't have any artificial flavors
or sweetness but they have managed to
make good tasting BCAA like this one
here is tropical punch as I mentioned
earlier it's very unusual for a
naturally flavored BCA product to be
made that isn't very sour because that's
normally the trade-off you have to make
when you're doing naturally flavored
BCAAs but these have like not very sour
tropical punch flavors they've also got
orange they've also got blue raspberry
in addition to more sour flavors like
sour green apple and strawberry lemonade
no matter which one you get you got to
enjoy the flavor we're a really big fan
of it transparent Labs also has our
favorite vegan BCAAs uh there is a
definite split between they generally
call them fermented BCAAs or vegan BCAAs
if you don't have fermented or vegan
before the BCAAs in your ingredients
list uh then they are not vegan they are
derived from animal products but you can
make a BCAAs in a vegan fashion and
that's what they're done here at
transparent Labs a couple other products
here also do the fermented ones but our
favorite vegan BCA supplement
is BCAA in glutamine from transparent
Labs next up we're going to talk about a
supplement with a name that sounds kind
of done by accent but what doesn't Nolly
Nolly Sports Nutrition has some really
cool branched chain amino acids here the
goal of these ones is to reduce muscle
soreness and improve recovery time and
we decided to name this one the best for
endurance and the best for women as well
the reason honestly is that when we talk
to our female readers and look at these
surveys taken in the uh in the industry
of Sports Nutrition female athletes they
tend to prefer products that don't have
a whole bunch of extraneous ingredients
to them right so it's a little bit
harder to Market them like really
overbuilt pre-workouts with a whole
bunch of different ingredients and
really high massive caffeine because
generally speaking female customers are
they want more minimalist strip back and
straightforward products so that's what
we feel Nolly has put together here so
this does a BCAA blend of five grams and
this is that there's very little else so
just a little bit of potassium which is
a helpful electrolyte that can help with
hydration and on top of that you get one
gram of fiber and you get a little bit
of red algae in here why they include
algae we believe it's because the source
of antioxidants that means it could help
to further improve recovery by providing
a bit of an anti inflammatory effects
lastly you can get it with caffeine or
without caffeine so without caffeine
it's going to be a nice stimulant free
thing to take before your workout but if
you are a runner if you're going to work
out
short of getting an actual pre-workout
and pre-workouts are going to have you
know hundreds of milligrams of caffeine
but if you want a more dedicated BCA
supplement with like a touch of caffeine
you get some organic green tea leaf
extracted caffeine here 35 milligrams
two of that into context an average 12
ounce cold brew from your local coffee
place is about 150 160 milligrams of
caffeine so that really is very very low
in caffeine if you want a dedicated it's
like strong caffeine supplement again
head to a pre-workout like this one but
if you want to get a proper BCA
supplement with just a bit of caffeine
to help to further enhance the endurance
effects that just plain BCAAs may have
we definitely recommend Nali all right
so next up we're going to have the best
BCAA capsules right so I'm a big fan of
taking supplements in capsule form right
which sounds a bit dumb because most
supplements are like vitamins and stuff
you take them in capsules but like
creatine I like to take in capsules BCAA
is the same the reason is it's simply
easier to take them on the go and it's
easier to lump them into the daily
supplements right we're a big fan of
optimum nutritions BCAA 1000 it is
nothing that BCAAs in a two to one to
one ratio of leucine isoleucine and
valine and they are encased in gelatin
capsules so ultimate directions BCAA
very plain no need for them to be
flavored really easy to transport with
you if you're on the go if you're taking
a trip if you want to do something with
your daily supplements uh in the morning
we're a big fan of these products you
should know that the gelatin the
capsules are in means that it's not
vegan friendly but these aren't vegan
friendly pcas in the first place so no
skin off our teeth but looking for some
BCA pills up nutrition is the best on
the market because this is a really big
company and that means they are pretty
competitively priced when it comes to
their supplements lastly we're going to
talk about the best branch team amino
acids for the keto diet keto diet very
high fat very low carbohydrate you want
the lowest carbohydrate lowest calorie B
series you can get the good news is most
of them are pretty down low in
carbohydrates but many of them contain
extra ingredients be it fillers be it
anti-caking agents be it flavorings that
kind of stuff that can sometimes bring
the carbohydrate count up tell you what
though cellucores Alpha Amino is less
than one gram of carbohydrate so yeah no
carbs here so very keto friendly that's
all you really need if you're looking
for something that can fit into a
ketogenic diet but there are extra
benefits here in that this has a wide
range of amino acids so like I said
earlier about a huge supplements BCAA
there can be some extra benefits extra
muscle retention benefits and so on to
having uh extra amino acids around your
BCAAs if you're taking less of a
minimalist approach to amino acid
supplement Alpha Amino has a whole Suite
of other amino acids more than anything
else on this list and it also has a
hydration blend so you know you're
getting some phosphorus magnesium sodium
potassium these are all electrolytes
that are helpful for hydration so it's a
really good supplement for just about
anybody
and I could hear it's extra good because
you might find it hard to find zero
carbohydrate BCA supplements Alpha Amino
we'll get you where you want to go so
that about doesn't man with a list of uh
the best BCA supplements um one question
I didn't want to address before we left
though is when to take BCAAs that's the
question that we hear a lot and it's
kind of a key to the whole thing right
like when you're talking about
pre-workouts you know you want to take
it 30 minutes before a workout we took a
BCA supplement there are more reasons
people take BCA supplements the timing
can vary based on like your individual
needs and purposes generally I would say
if you are someone who likes to take
your BCAAs because you're attracted to
the muscle retention and endurance
benefits that are associated with them
for your workouts yeah you take it
before a workout I'd say like 30 minutes
before a workout maybe even an hour for
a workout but yeah 36 minutes before a
workout that should get it into your
belly and ideally into your bloodstream
at least if you're on an empty stomach
so before a workout you don't want to
have like a really really full stomach
for one because it'll take longer for
your pre-workout BCAAs to absorb and
digest and get into your bloodstream for
two if you have a really full stomach
which is full of protein amino acids
it's unlikely you need the BCAAs in the
first place so you want to make sure
you've eaten like at least an hour
before a workout so that your stomach is
like empty enough you can take these
BCAAs and have them contribute to your
workout if you are someone who is taking
BCAAs to stimulate muscle protein
synthesis throughout the day that's
another very common reason to take in uh
Tim Ferriss does it when he's having his
longer fast he sits on BCAAs so that he
can prevent as much muscle loss as
possible this is a pretty broad rule but
for people who take BCAAs because they
are going a long time without protein
and want to maintain muscle protein
synthesis as best they can I would say
wait a good six hours without food
before you might want to think about
stimulating muscle protein synthesis
again there's nothing wrong with taking
it earlier like that's the thing with
BCAAs you can just take them whenever
you want but if your concern is how long
without food is it going to take until
it might be a good idea to think about
stimulating muscle protein synthesis
yeah I think probably six hours and if
you're fasting like you're not eating
all day you can just uh sip it
throughout the day I think every every
three to six hours would be would be
fine to have your BCAAs again nothing
wrong with happening more often than
that you just have to think about
balancing the amount of calories that
you'll be consuming with your goals
maintaining the project emphasis the
last thing I want to see here is muscle
protein synthesis which is the main
thing with BCAAs that is part of the
muscle gain puzzle and muscle retention
puzzle It Is by no means all of it uh
when it comes to especially muscle gain
it also muscle retention there's all
these other aspects to think about like
muscle like protein turnover meaning are
you making sure that you are gaining or
retaining muscle faster than you are
losing it there's also total calories
there's total protein intake there's
your workouts there's your sleep is all
of the stuff to it so BCAAs they could
be a useful tool in your kit when it
comes to the question of muscle
retention and also potentially for
endurance and focus during your workouts
as well that said please do not forget
all the other much bigger more important
pieces of the puzzle when it comes to
maintaining your physique that's a video
on Branch chain amino acids if you want
to be able to take this information in
at your own speed you can go to the
article you can Google barban best BCAAs
this whole thing is going to come up and
you can read it at your own pace and
check out the studies we've been talking
about and make up your own mind as to
whether or not BCAAs are for you or not
that's it hope you learned something see
you next video
[Music]